hello and welcome it's September 18th
2023 and it's active guest stream 57.1
with Andy Keller we're going to be
talking about natural neural structure
for artificial intelligence there will
be a presentation followed by a
discussion so if you're watching live
please feel free to write questions in
the live chat otherwise thank you Andy
for this really looking forward to it
and to you for the
presentation yeah thanks so much uh
thanks for having me I'm super excited
to be able to present this stuff with
the active inference group I'm a a fan
and very interested so hopefully uh yeah
get to have a good discussion and see
what you guys think about it um so my
name's Andy I'm finishing up my PhD
supervised by Max Welling at the
University of Amsterdam um and starting
up St pert after this so I'll start out
um just talking about the goal of my
work in general is to try to bring
modern artificial intelligence closer to
more humanlike generalization and so
what we mean by this is maybe some sort
of structured
generalization um or maybe more familiar
to the active inference Community like a
structured World model which we believe
that humans have and the way that we
propose to do this is by integrating
natural neural structure into to
artificial
intelligence so first let's define what
we mean by structure generalization so I
think it's fairly uncontroversial to say
that modern machine learning generalizes
Beyond its training set in the
traditional sense so for example even
the earliest artificial neural networks
multi-layer perceptrons could be trained
on data sets of images like this uh and
Achieve high accuracy then when they're
presented with a heldout test set of
images that they've never seen before
they can still classify them relatively
easily with the same level of accuracy
and this is what we typically call
generalization however even fairly early
on it was noticed that these systems
really struggle with small shifts or
deformations applied to the images for
example
if model so we think why is this
surprising um and I argue it's really
due to our innate ability to perform
this type of structure generalization
that this example is a failure
so uh for example this shift is nearly
imperceptible to us and we handle it
automatically whereas in the systems
it's very clearly a major problem so in
words we can say that structure
generalization is a generalization to
some symmetry transformations of the
input or in this case the Symmetry
transformation is a small shift that
leaves the digit class
unchanged so the obvious question then
is what precisely do we mean by this
natural structure and why do we think
that this would help us with the
settings so first let's talk about what
we mean by natural neural structure um
one way to talk about structure or or
any type of uh bias in a system is an
inductive bias and so an inductive bias
can Loosely be defined as an opior
restriction of a set of realizable
hypotheses when you're doing model
selection um more colloquially we can
call this something like the forseeing
any data it's a restriction of what and
how you can learn so very broadly this
can include anything from model class to
optimization procedures or even
hyperparameters um and in some sense
they really Define what is uh what is
possible to learn and it defines
generalization and that you actually
can't generalize Beyond a training set
without having some inductive biases and
this is explained more thoroughly in
this paper by David Wolford so what we
mean by natural inductive biases then is
biases that stem from the restrictions
and limitations that are faced by
natural systems uh by the nature of
having to live in the real world for
example the brain has many efficiency
constraints and physical constraints
ping sure of its construction uh and
following this logic then these
constraints are really playing some role
in our generalization abilities which
currently exceed modern artificial
intelligence as we go into next so in
this talk I'll be focusing specifically
on two types of structure which my work
has studied uh these are are topographic
organization and spao temporal Dynamics
and before I go into my work I'll give a
short example for why I believe that
natural structure may be useful to
achieve the structure generalization
that I was talking about
before so the first example comes from
uh fukushima's neocognitron architecture
from the 1980s which was actually which
was actually built to directly address
the problem of robustness to these small
shifts and deformations so in the paper
he it's about inspiration from pbil and
weasel's measurements of hierarchy and
pooling in order to achieve robustness
to these distortions and so if you look
at the figure he writes U sub S1 U sub
C1 and these stand for simple and
complex cells um and so this was a
fairly radical Approach at the time but
it really served to improve robustness
and shifts that were plaguing these
early artificial neural networks and
over time these ideas were simplified
and abstracted and obviously yielded the
convolutional neuron networks that we
know today which ultimately drove the
success of the deep learning Revolution
so this is really an example of a
natural inductive bias which achieved
structured generalization so for our
research it's really of utmost interest
to try and understand what makes these
models work so well um and see if this
principle can potentially be generalized
to cover more AB more abstract
Transformations and
symmetries so what makes a convolution a
achieve this structure
generalization intuitively you can see
this is done by applying the same filter
at or or feature extractor at various
spatial locations so here we see a
single convolutional filter being
applied at all locations of an image and
this means that no matter where your
input is whether it's kind of in the
middle of the image or on the right
you'll have the exact same features with
one exception they'll be equivalently
shifted so mathematically this type of a
mapping is called a homomorphism it
preserves the algebra structure of the
input space and the output space in this
case is with respect to translation and
at a simple a simple level something
like that will be important to remember
for the rest of this talk is that we can
verify homomorphisms of our feature
extractor uh if we can see that there's
this Comm commutation with the the
transformation this communative diagram
and so we can write this also
algebraically by showing that the
feature extractor f commutes with the
transformation operator T and basically
what we want is there to be no
difference between first extracting the
features and then performing the
transformation or performing the
transformation and then extracting the
features so the challenges to date is we
don't really know how to construct
homomorphisms with respect to more
complex Transformations that we see in
the real world for example our brain is
able to handle changes in lighting and
season naturally um so here we see
Lighting on a person's face or the
change of seasons we can tell it's the
same face or the the same road um but we
don't know how how to build models which
respect these Transformations and so it
makes us hard to build systems which
handle them in a robust and predictable
way to give an even more abstract
example of what I mean by this and the
potential negative repercussions of
models which don't handle symmetry
Transformations uh consider modern text
to image generation programs so in this
example I asked Dolly 2 to generate a
image of a teddy bear on the moon and it
does this incredibly well right probably
better than I could it has texture for
uh incredibly detailed however if I ask
it to do something which I see is
conceptually simpler such as draw a blue
cube on top of a Red Cube it fails to do
this and to me this seems unintuitive
since the second task seems
significantly easier um but what I'm
arguing is that the reason that this is
surprising is precisely the same reason
that the mnus translation example was
surprising there's this symmetry
transformation Happening Here namely the
transformation between these complex
objects of a teddy bear in the moon and
these simple objects of Cubes which we
intuitively expect the network to be
able to handle and respect and we see
that it doesn't so just like how
fukushima's work showed that these
natural structure of hierarchy and
pooling of our visual system are
effective for making generalizations to
small Transformations uh I argue that
potentially higher level structure may
be necessary to fix these abstract
generalization
problems and so the the question then
that I'm studying and that I'm asking is
uh what might this structure be and how
do we implement this in a artificial
neural network architecture that can
actually be used for performing
computation so to begin to answer that
I'll jump into my first line of work on
topographic
organization so topographic organization
uh is observed widely throughout the
brain from primary visual cortex to
higher level areas and it can very
Loosely be described as this property
that neurons which are close to one
another tend to respond to similar
things for example on the left we show
the colorcoded preprints of each neuron
in the Mako primary visual cortex uh as
a response to oriented lines and we see
this smoothly varying set of
selectivities another type of
organization is known as retinotopic
organization where nearby neurons in the
visual cortex tend to respond to nearby
receptive
Fields however this organization isn't
limited to these lowlevel field features
it extends up to more complex features
such as those present in faces or
objects or places and this relates to
the so-called functionally specific
areas of the brain such as the fusiform
face area FFA and the parip temple face
area
PPA so in in this work the main idea
again is that perhaps this topographic
organization in some sense which is
intimately related to the convolution
operation and fush architecture uh we
can maybe generalize the benefits of
this to more abstract transformations in
other words learn how to build more
complex homomorphisms that we can't do
that we can't do analytically right
now so just to show that we're not
completely insane with this idea uh
there is some prior work in this domain
from people such as uh honen y aparin in
the early 90s and and 2000s and they
studied how topographic organization may
be useful for learning invariances
mostly in linear models so the question
for us when we entered the space is what
is the most scalable abstract mechanism
that can be leveraged from these
approaches which we can integrate into
modern deep neural network architectures
and ultimately we settled on a
generative model modeling approach which
I think might be interesting to the
people in this community um which then
allows us to relate it more closely to
topographic independent component
analysis with the basic idea being that
we can learn a topographic feature Space
by proposing a topographic prior
distribution over our latent
variables so just to give a brief
background I assume most people are
already familiar with this um but the
kind of General assumption is that the
brain is a generative model and this
idea in some sense can be attributed to
helmholtz from the 19th century uh where
he said that what we see is the solution
to a computational problem our brains
compute the most likely causes from
Photon absorptions within our eyes and
so as an examp example if I show you
this image you immediately recognize it
as a globe with some curvature however
it could just as equally be a dis with a
distorted perspective on it so this is
how we get optical illusions or or
images so like this one your brain
infers that there is a cube here because
of the structure but really it's just a
flat piece of paper so you can think of
this generative model aspect that's kind
of like an inverse Graphics program in
the program the abstract properties of
the sphere are known the position the
size the lighting and these are used to
project the sphere to create the 2D
image that is rendered so in effect what
Holtz and others are saying is that as a
generative model the brain is actually
trying to invert this generative process
and doing inference and infer the
underlying causes of our Sensations so
the reason I'm kind of belaboring this
point is that there's a lot of talk of
generative models today um and I'm not
necessarily just talking about
generating images or pretty pictures um
I really want to
mean a framework for unsupervised
learning so then to get a little bit
more into the details what do I mean by
a topographic prior so generative models
are typically described as a joint
distribution over observations X and
latent variables which we'll call Z uh
and this is typically factorized or one
way that this is done is factorized in
terms of a prior P of Z and this true
generative model conditional generative
model P of x given Z and so one way that
we can think about this is that the
prior can be seen to encode relative
penalties for each type of code that is
produced when we invert our generative
model this is called Computing the
posterior e ofz given
x uh and so to develop a topographic
latent space we want to introduce some
sort of a topographic prior which has
been or which this topographic ICA work
showed is equivalent to something like a
group sparsity penalty
so people might be familiar with typical
sparsity penalties from independent
component analysis you want your
activations to be sparse meaning many of
them are
zero so that could look something like
this you have a bunch of blue squares
that are active but most of them are not
active but specifically with a group
sparsity penalty we want these priors to
assign lower probability to these
distributed sparse activations and
higher probability to these grouped
densely packed representations you can
also think of this like a higher penalty
when things are spread out a lower
penalty when things are closer
together so again uh this can be written
abstractly like this but I want to make
clear that these neuron it each one of
these squares here represents kind of a
neuron in our model and they're
organized in this 2D grid so when we're
talking about grouping we really mean
grouping in that 2D
topology um so one thing that's really
interesting and kind of important uh is
that these priors don't just give us
topographic organization but they've
also been noted by people like or
studied by people like Ros Manelli and
Bruno Olen uh to to actually fit the
statistics of natural data better uh
specifically natural images uh they've
shown that using this type of a prior
you actually get a sparer set of
activations meaning that the prior fits
the true generative process a little bit
better and as we're aware the brain has
a high degree of sparsity uh and this is
believed to be very relevant for
efficiency so so to get a little bit
more into the details to implement this
type of a group sparse prior we use a
hierarchical generative model and this
is uh basically introduced by some of
the topographic ICA work um the idea is
that you have a higher level latent
variable U which simultaneously
regulates the variance of multiple lower
level variables T and this is how we get
group
sparsity then to get topographic
organization you can have multiple of
these latent variables used slightly
over overlapping with their fields of
influence so their uh their
neighborhoods we can call them and this
will give you this smooth correlation
structure you're act you're after so get
the intuition for this you see that this
variable T over down on the bottom here
is not getting any input from this U on
the top but it is sharing a u variable
with this T in the middle so it's like
they're sharing variants they're sharing
some components with their neighbors but
not all components and that's really due
to this local connectivity of these
higher level variables you
so to keep it simple about how we use a
generative model let's go back to a
single U variable and the challenge in
this type of an architecture which made
it difficult for for many years is how
do you infer the approximate posterior
over these intermediate latent variables
in this hierarchical architecture um and
this is not super straightforward so
prior Works have use heuristics
developed for linear models and in our
work we found that these really didn't
extend to Modern Network architectures
so really our Insight is to leverage a
factorization a specific
reparameterization of this
distribution and so this
reparameterization specifically is
achieved by defining the prior to be
what's known as a a gaan scale mixture
meaning that our conditional
distribution of T given U is actually a
normal distribution where the the
variance is defined by uh this variable
U and for certain choices of U this
distribution is indeed spar and
encompasses a range of distributions
such as laosan and Su T distributions
one way of defining it is a gaoui scale
mixture admits a particular repar
reparameterization in terms of
independent gausian random variables Z
and U so specifically then we we see
that this T variable which was
originally fairly complex is actually
just a product of a bunch of gausin Rand
of variables which we now know how to
work with much more efficiently uh in in
generative models and specifically what
we're going to do is so that we can
actually get approximate posteriors for
U and Z separately and then do a
deterministic combination of them in
order to compute our topographic
variable T and this is much easier to do
so without going into too many details
um the method that we decide to use is
what's known as a variational auto
encoder which leverages techniques from
variational inference uh to derrive a
lower bound on the likelihood allowing
us to parameterize these approximate
posteriors with powerful linear deep
neural networks and optimize them with
gradient descent uh this is going to be
familiar to the active inference
Community but really what we've done is
instead of having a single encoder and
decoder as is typical vaes we now have
two encoders one for U and one for Z
separately and then we combine them in
this deterministic manner to construct
our topographic T variable uh if you see
that this is a this actually the
construction of a a student te
distribution from
gaussians uh and then we can plug this
we do this before decoding and uh and
then maximize the likelihood of the data
altogether so this is the elbow the
evidence lower bound abound on the
likelihood of the data and is actually
uh very similar to the variational free
energy that uh is used in active
inference
community so with with these details out
of the way what's really interesting is
what happens when we train this
generative model which has relatively
simple group sparsity penalty in its
Laten space uh and we want to look at
kind of what it's learning in terms of
its organization of features and first
we start with the simplest possible data
set we have a black background with
white squares at random XY locations and
if we train our autoencoder with this
group sparcity penalty on it and then we
look at the weight vectors of our
decoder uh which we're plotting in blue
here again organized in this 2D grid uh
we see that indeed they learn to be
organized according to spatial location
so this can be seen as similar to
convolutional receptive Fields where the
receptive field of each neuron is really
given by the the kind of input at its
location and this makes sense
intuitively from the group sparsity
perspective since for any given region
which you highlight like in yellow here
the filters in a given group are much
more highly correlated they have these
overlapping receptive Fields than other
random locations so essentially we see
that our model is learning to Cluster
activ activities together
uh in sort of a simulated cortical sheet
uh according to the correlations in the
data set so instead of in convolution
where you're actually doing weight tying
and you're manually specifying I want to
copy this weight everywhere you can
maybe think of this as like approximate
weight tying um and really we're
learning this from the correlation
structure of the data set itself and
just to give a little bit more of a
biological inspiration for this and we
know that retinotopy is present in the
brain this is an example of reat Toopy
in the MCO visual cortex uh and you can
see if you show the Maco an image like
this it gets projected into this uh
topology preserving uh space actually on
the surface of the
cortex so the idea is that topographic
organization and even learn topographic
organization is preserving the input
correlations of our data set uh and and
potentially uh this may be beneficial
for generalizing these ideas a little
bit further so like I said at the
beginning uh it would be even better if
we could just learn something more than
just convolution maybe more complicated
equiv variances so how do we do that one
thing that's clear in natural
intelligence is that we don't exist in
this world of IID frames right we exist
in a world with continuous sequences of
Transformations so maybe we can extend
our model to this setting to learn
observe Transformations this is the idea
of temporal
coherence so what would happen if we
just simply extended our previous
framework over the time Dimension right
so instead of just grouping saying we
want our neurons to be group sparse in
terms of spatial extent on the cortex we
actually want them to be group sparse
over time meaning that if one set of
neurons is active now we want that same
set of neurons to be active into the
future as
well if we look at if we kind of
intuitively think about this
we see that this is actually more
encouraging invariance than equivariance
a way to understand this is we're saying
we want the same neurons to be active
constantly but the input transformation
is changing right the the feet of this
little fox are moving so if the same
neurons are coding for the same thing
over and over again but the feet are
moving those neurons are going to learn
to be invariant to the motion of that
leg of this dog for example so instead
is that
oops I went the wrong way here
uh so instead uh our Insight was that
this group starcity could instead be
shifted with respect to time so this
would mean that sequentially shifted
sets of activations would be encouraged
to activate together and then our latent
space would really be structured with
respect to the observed Transformations
so you can see here that rather than the
same set of neurons being active at all
time steps it's really a sequentially
permuted set of neurons that were
grouping together in this sparse way uh
and and then this allows us to model
different observations over time but
they're still connected in terms of
learning a transformation and preserving
this correlation structure of the input
data set so if we put this together into
our topographic vae architecture you can
get something that looks like this you
see that we have an input sequence we're
again encoding a a z variable and then
multiple U variables in the denominator
here um and then each one of these U
variables is shifted uh kind of like we
were showing before in order to achieve
this this shift equivariant structure
that we're looking for when we combine
these in this student T product
distribution we get a single latent
variable this is now our topographic
latent variable T and now that we have
this known structure in our latent space
you can think of it like a structured
World model we know how to transform
this latent space in this case it's by
permuting these activations around these
circles during like a cyclic roll a
cyclic shift we know that this is going
to correspond to our learned input
Transformations and we can verify that
by saying okay what if I continue this
input transformation the true
transformation in the data set which is
a rotation and then I compare that with
how I've done my role in my lat Space by
moving my activations around in my brain
and then we decode and we see that we
get the exact same thing and so this is
demonstrating this commuity property
that I was talking about before for
verifying
homomorphism and so to measure this
little bit more qual
quantitatively uh we can measure what's
called an equivariance loss so this is
really the quantification of this
difference between our rolled capsule
activation our rolling in our head
versus watching the rolling of unfold in
for they're watching the transformation
unfold before us so we see that
topographic Bae achieves significantly
lower uh equivariance error this bubble
vae is what I was talking about before
where it's learning invariance so it
doesn't have this shift operation and
the traditional VA kind of has no notion
of organization or temporal component so
it performs very poorly um in addition
to this we see that the model is a
better generative model of sequences it
just gets a lower or lower like negative
log likelihood uh on the data set so
it's it's better able to model this data
set because it has a notion of the
structure of the
Transformations uh we can test this on
multiple different transformation Types
on the top row we're showing the true
transformation we hold out these grade
out images and then on the bottom row we
encode and then we just kind of roll our
activations around and we keep decoding
to see what the what the
model uh has learned as the current
transformation that's being observed and
we see that it can basically perfectly
reconstruct these elements of the
sequence that it's never seen before
additionally with images that are from
the test set that it's never seen before
simply because it knows what the
transformation is that it's currently
encoding and it can generalize that to
new
examples so the takeaway from this part
is really topographic organization we
show that it preserved input structure
and now we're showing it can potentially
improve efficiency and generalization as
we would hope uh that a structured world
world model would be able to do so
finally something that surprised us and
I thought was potentially the most
interesting is that these these
Transformations that are learned by our
model actually generalize the
combinations of transform
that were not seen during training so
for example despite only training on
color and rotation transformations in
isolation if the model is presented with
a combined color rotation transformation
at test time uh we we see that it's able
to completely model and and complete
these Transformations perfectly through
the capsule role uh implying that it's
learned a factorized representation with
respect to these different
Transformations and it can flexibly
combine them at inference time
so again maybe we also don't just get
effic efficiency in generalization we
also get some basic
compositionality so let's talk about the
limitations and and what we could do
next uh the main limitation is that
there's a predefined transformation that
we're imposing uh in both space and time
so although we freed ourselves from
group Transformations and specifically
like uh translation or rotation as is
currently done in the machine learning
world
um we still have uh this hardcoded
latent role in our heads for everything
we see and to make this a little bit
more flexible so hopefully we can model
a greater diversity of
Transformations um we we think maybe we
can take inspiration from more
structured spatiotemporal dynamics that
are observed in the brain and so that
takes us to the the second part of this
talk which is uh spao temporal dynamics
that we're going to try to integrate
into artificial neural networks one one
example of that is traveling waves like
I showed here so what do we mean by that
uh here's a very recent paper where they
used a nine Tesla fmri operating at 36
millisecond resolution to image a single
slice of a rat brain under anesthesia
and what we see is this very clearly
structured spatio temporal activity and
correlations and these authors of the
paper go on to analyze this activity in
terms of the principal modes as depicted
on the right so our Hy hypthesis is that
perhaps some sort of a correlation
structure like this may be beneficial
for structuring the representations of
our model with respect to observe
Transformations but in a much more
flexible way than simply just a cck
shift like we were doing
before
um and let me say that this is not just
observed in anesthesized rats uh this
you can see these traveling waves happen
in the Mt cortex of awake behaving
primates uh so for example on the left
here they show traveling waves that
actually uh change How likely a primate
is to see a low contrast stimuli based
on the the phase of the wave uh
furthermore they show that the like a
high contrast stimulus on the right uh
can induce a traveling wave of activity
that propagates outwards even in primary
visual C cortex so these are really
ubiquitous throughout the brain at
multiple levels and it would be
interesting to study what their
implications are for uh structure
representation learning in our case or
or
generally there is PRI work which has
studied these types of uh Dynamics and
they built models so on the top these
are the equations which describe a
spiking neural network which they show
if you implement uh time delays actually
Exon time delays between neurons you do
get these structur dynamics of uh
traveling waves as long as your network
size is large enough um however
as many people probably know it's
relatively challenging to train spiking
neural networks of the same size and
performance as as teep neural networks
um similarly on the bottom another
system which is significantly simpler
but perhaps too simple uh is a network
of coupled oscillators these are known
to exhibit synchrony and uh spatial
temporal Dynamics and complex patterns
but uh this is called like a phase
reduced system and does quite capture
the full complexity that we're
interested in so we're looking at
something that's potentially in between
these two and what we settled on as this
work in this work is uh to parameterize
a network of coupled oscillators
slightly more flexibly than a camoto
model so this is really built on this
couple dilatory recurrent neural network
of Constantine R and nishra um where
they basically took the equation which
describes a simple harmonic oscillator
it's a second order differential
equation
the acceleration on a ball on a spring
is proportional to its
displacement uh you can add additional
terms such as damping so that the
oscillations slowly die out over
time you can drive this oscillator with
an external input to kind of counteract
this damping or to give slightly more
complexity to the
Dynamics and then furthermore if you
have many of these oscillators you can
couple them together with these coupling
matrices W uh as we demonst kind of in
this picture here so you can really
think of this network as a bunch of
balls on Springs and they're may be
connected to each other also by Springs
or elastic bands whatever you want um
and this is the couple dilatory
recurrent neural network of of rushan
Mishra uh with these various terms and
this has been shown to be very powerful
for modeling long sequences they also
mentioned they were inspired by the
brain building this and there's a lot of
good analysis in that paper uh for
example they show that this has really
beneficial properties with respect to uh
Vanishing gradient problems that
typically happen in recurrent networks
um but if we want to look at spatio
temporal Dynamics in this type of a
model uh it's slightly challenging
because these coupling matrices here the
W's uh that that connect each neur or
each oscillator positioned to one
another um these are densely connected
matrices like I've tried to depict on
the left here so if you try to visualize
the Dynamics of this network uh you
don't see any spatial organization
there's no in
topology to the latent space of this
model um so you can think of this like
in our previous example a neuron is
connected to a potentially arbitrary set
of other neurons those neurons are
connected to another arbitrary set of
neurons and you'll just get a cator
Dynamics certainly but kind of
fluctuations that don't make a lot of
structured
sense so in our work then we thought
okay how can we convert this more to the
the types of dynamics that we're
interested in this structured
propagation of it uh and one clear way
to do that is to have a more structured
connectivity Matrix W uh which we found
is easily implemented and efficiently
implemented through a convolution
operation which you can think of like a
local a locally connected layer so
instead of having every neuron connected
to every neuron neurons are just
connected to their nearby neighbors and
then you after training you'll end up
getting something that looks like a
smooth spacial temporal
Dynamics so to be a little bit more
clear to train this model we take this
second order differential equation that
we were describing before you discretize
it into two first order equations you
can think of this as like numerically
integrating the OD uh we now have a
velocity and then we update the
positions with this
velocity uh and and we can train this
model as something like an autoencoder
or an auto regressive model so we take
an input we encode it to our latent
space really the input is D is this F
ofx term which acts as the driving term
so it's like driving these oscillators
from from the bottom uh and then they
have their own Dynamics which are
defined by the coupling terms these
local couplings and then at each time
step we take this latent State this wave
state and we decode to try and
reconstruct the input be at the current
time step or a future time
step we can do some analysis of of these
models uh during training uh to see what
happens before training and after
training we can compute the phase and
the velocity of the Dynamics in the
latent space basically we see at the
beginning of training there's no waves
in our model but after training after 50
epochs we see that there's these smooth
structured activity propagating
downwards uh in service of this sequence
modeling task that we're doing like
rotating
objects um so what's what's the benefit
of this I mean the whole reason I
motivated this was to say we wanted to
have more flexibly learned structure are
we actually doing that or are we just
getting pretty waves um so what we
showed in our paper is that we really
are learning some sort of useful
structure and the way we showed that is
again with something like this
communitive diagram if you take an input
and you encode it and you get a wave
state and then you propagate waves
artificially in that wave state and then
decode you can observe that it's
actually exactly the same as if you had
just performed that transformation in
the input space originally so what we're
in effect showing here is the commuity
of our feature extractor and the
transformation and in our case the
transformation the operator in the
latent space is now a traveling wave of
activity and so in a sense it is
structuring our latent space with
respect to observe Transformations that
structure comes in the form of waves so
natural spao temporal structure yields
preserved input structure again as we
were looking
for um and and one of the benefits of
this as opposed to previously is that
now this is slightly more flexible and
we can see this just by showing a bunch
of different images of different
Transformations so of different uh
digits different features and we see
that we get different types of wave
activity in each case in order to model
that different transformation if we
train it on different data sets as well
we similarly see more complex Dynamics
in this case maybe not even traveling
waves or standing waves which can be
thought of as uh traveling waves in
opposite directions so we see if we're
modeling these orbital Dynamics we get
these kind of smoothly moving Blobs of
activity in lat space if we're modeling
a pendulum we simp Lally get kind of
complex hillory
activity so it's preserved input
structure but additionally more
flexibility than we had before which is
kind of our ultimate
goal so finally I I want to talk a bit
about how I think the outcome of This
research may not only improve artificial
intelligence but also how it helps us
understand why our measurements of the
brain look the way they do so to give a
brief example of what I mean by this uh
I talked about bit about before about
these localized areas that respond to
faces and places uh so in this fantastic
work with chinga we studied if our
simple topographic prior as we discussed
may be able to reproduce these same
effects so specifically we plot the
value of this Co andd selectivity metric
for each of our neurons with respect to
a different data set of images
potentially containing just faces or
just objects or bodies and so we measure
for every neuron is it more likely to
respond to faces or the rest of the
images and we see that we get these
spatially localized clusters uh that
that share many of the properties that
we actually see in the visual system of
of humans and primates in many animals
so uh one one of these properties that's
shared Beyond just the fact that we have
these spatially localized clusters is
like the the relative placement of faces
and bodies we see that the face cluster
is overlapping with the body cluster
which is uh makes a lot of sense and is
also seen in humans and faces and bodies
are most often seen together um and this
isn't just a
single uh a single fluke or a
cherry-picked example if we rerun this
model many times you virtually always
get placed in body clusters which are
overlapping or right next to one each
other one another so to be clear I'm not
suggesting that this is exactly how the
brain works or how topographic
organization emerges in the brain uh but
I do think that it tells us that the
relative organization of selectivity May
at least be partially attributable to
correlation statistics in the data after
be P after being passed through a highly
nonlinear feature extractor such as a
deep neural network so in a similar vein
something that's interesting there's a
known what's called tripartite
organization uh the visual stream so uh
images of uh or objects are selectivity
with respect to objects is organized by
more abstract properties such as animacy
is this thing alive or animate uh versus
also real world object size like what is
the size of a teapot versus a car um and
what we see is that in the in humans
this this selectivity is organized in
this tripartite structure you typically
have small objects that are in between
the animate and inanimate objects in
terms of their selectivity and we see
the same thing kind of happens here so
these are measuring the selectivity of
the same set of neurons but with respect
to these different sets of stimuli we
see the the small cluster is in between
anim and an an cluster again this
happens for multiple different
initializations so this is something I
hope we can explore a bit further for
this community I think it's interesting
because it's it's really a way of
showing that we built a a structured
World model and potentially this world
model is beneficial for better
representing real world data in a
structured way and you get lower free
energy in that sense so
um yeah I think by developing these
model models like like we showed here we
may get insights into new mechanisms for
how this structure emerges uh including
topographic organization that we never
thought of before so as an example in in
developing this neural wave Machine
model I was looking at the orientation
selectivity uh of neurons I wasn't
particularly expecting something to
happen but uh you're looking at kind of
these waves Pro propagate over this
simulated cortical surface and I thought
okay maybe I'm showing rotated images
maybe this has some effect on the
orientation
selectivity and actually if you go in
and you measure the selectivity of each
neuron with respect to these differently
oriented lines what you see is that it's
surprisingly reminiscent of the
orientation columns and Hyper columns
that are seen in primary visual cortex
this is stuff going back to hugle and
weasel and this is something that just
kind of came out of this model and the
fact that it has the spatial temporal
structure with respect to transformation
so uh of course this is really course
analogy but I think this is an example
of how building these types of models
can help us think about how the brain
builds representational structure and
the why the way it's organized in a way
that maybe we haven't thought about
before um I think I'm not the only one
who's doing this type of work and and so
I want to talk a little bit about some
other people who are doing this uh so
I've been talking about like this
equivariant structure um people such as
James Whittington and Tim Barons and sir
ganguli uh have shown recently that by
introducing algebraic constraints into
uh into a learning process in this case
it was like the motion of a an an agent
in an environment by saying you need to
preserve kind of this algebraic
structure of if I move in a a circle
west north east south I end up back at
the same Point again um by introducing
these types of constraints you get the
emergence of grid cell like
representations um so I'd be interested
to see how this idea of representational
structure can help us explain maybe more
the neuroscientific findings we're
finding as well um and and how this
relates to generative models as a
whole um and then finally I think
there's something to be said about
cognitive plausibility of these models
as well maybe we're not just going to be
testing them from a neuroscience
perspective but also from a cognitive
science perspective for example there's
these uh Ravens Progressive matrices on
the left where you have this like say
which one of these images is more likely
to fit in this pattern um or for example
How likely is it that this Jenga Tower
Falls over when you pull over a pull a
specific block or or or with a given
structure um and I think these things
are these types of tests are really
testing if our world models that we're
building are similar to the types of
models that we innately have our own
common sense as as humans or as beings
living in a a natural world um and I've
done some preliminary work in this
direction I think very uh preliminary
and not nearly this complicated but um
trying to model visual Illusions so if
you take a really simple data set of a
moving bar stimuli or a static bar and
you flash you you take out a frame and
you move it a little bit you can see
that the model will actually infer that
missing frame and then actually also
infer continued motion so it's like
overshooting the trajectory of what the
actual stimuli is providing it um before
correcting again so I think modeling
Illusions is certainly an interesting
way to study if our world models are
similar to the types of models that we
have
ourselves so in conclusion uh yeah I
think topographic priors we could show
that they effectively learn structured
representations or structured World
models this learn structure is flexible
and adaptable to arbitrary
Transformations unlike traditional
equivariant and topograph Riders can be
induced statistically as in the
topographic vae or through Dynamics like
we were showing in these neural wave
machine type models so to conclude I'll
I'll leave you with this quote that I
found in fukushima's paper from 1980 I
thought was uh pretty far ahead of its
time where he says if we could make a
neural network model which has the same
capability for pattern recognition as a
human being it would give us a powerful
clue to the mechanism of the neural
mechan or understanding the neural
mechanism in the brain uh so that's kind
of I think some of the goals that we're
going for here so I'll say thanks to my
adviser Max my co-authors Patrick UA
Emil jingen and Y and interested in
discussion
thanks all
right all right thank you great very uh
interesting
presentation a lot of places to start
maybe just uh what what brought you to
this work a little context on how you
came into this work for your PhD
Direction yeah um I mean my group has
been studying not my the group that I'm
in and the university has been studying
structured representations from a
mathematical point of view for a while
and we're some of the people to
introduce equivariant neural networks as
well as generative models or for like
the variational a coder um
and I guess what something that had
always
been somewhat challenging to me uh is
that these structured representations
were fairly rigidly defined in terms of
group structure mathematical group
structure um so for example we can build
a model that respects rotations 2D
rotations perfectly well but if we want
to do 3D rotations we can't do that
because that's not a group in terms of a
projection onto a 2d plane there's
you're losing information when this
thing rotates around for example
um or just any sort of natural
Transformations like I was trying to
plan out at the beginning I think it was
trying to think about how the brain
models natural Transformations is
something that this these current
Frameworks couldn't really explain um
and yeah my adviser Max was had worked
on this topographic stuff uh a long time
ago during his postto and so he kind of
had this intuition that maybe
topographic organization has a
relationship here um then Co happened
and I got really deep in Neuroscience
literature and uh got into this stuff
and yeah haven't left
over
cool where do you see action playing a
role in terms of variational autoencoder
models that include not
just external patterns but also the
consequences of action or World model
structure structure with
action right yeah no that's a good
question I think active inference is uh
is effectively the the answer to that I
mean I think it's a good answer to that
um I know there
are reinforcement learning Frameworks
that do use use kind of externally
trained World models so you train a VA
or something and then you use that
representation in in your reinforcement
learning system um but I think having a
fully kind of a system that is a single
objective with uh action as part of the
likelihood of the data and uh yeah I
think that's much more elegant and and
so I'm a big proponent of that
um I have not gotten so far as to study
how these structured World models in a
vae or I haven't worked on that at all
but I think it would certainly be very
interesting to see if having a more
structured World
model uh in a variational auto encoder
would be beneficial in in an active
setting as well I think that would be
awesome I mean I think some of these
examples like uh showing before like
emergence of grid cells and things like
this maybe Point towards that direction
of hey maybe the brain is doing
something it's really obviously has a
lot of structure um this clearly has to
be useful for performing actions in some
way oh yeah I thought a really nice
parallel that you brought in with a talk
was the locally connected units enabled
your models to structurally embody the
convolutional constraint and pattern and
that led to these arising patterns and
then analogously there was the uh Doral
at all where they had the path
exploration constraint right and so then
it's interesting to to um you know think
about these action or policy heris STS
or sparsities like a joint through
babbling and motor exploration
eventually it becomes understood that
there's like two mutually opposing ways
to move a joint and then the
compositionality across joints can can
be learned to the higher levels once
it's locked in at lower levels so it's a
very
appealing and
uh uh Niche relevant way to generalize
because it's both based upon the actual
constraints of the world but then
especially through action potentially
embedding something that's quite
simple right yeah no I think that's
definitely true that's a really good
point if uh if you do have constraints
coming from your actions and themselves
then that's that would be hugely
beneficial for helping to to structure
your your lat and space and I think yeah
I guess one thing I wanted to mention
there's um something made me think of
like Stefano Fu's work on kind of the
representational
geometry uh and how
that determines how we
how how generalizable a given
understanding of a system is uh and I
think if you can understand your
representations in terms of geometry of
like these uh sets of activities are
separable or highly parallel separable
with a linear classifier essentially uh
then you're going to be able to do
generalization and I think by imposing
these types of biases or potentially
through constraints that are imposed by
action something like this you are
yielding or kind of inducing a better
representational geometry and this has
all sorts of benefits for like
compositionality
or yeah or generalization so it's a
great Point cool yeah very interesting
area all right I'll read some questions
from the live chat love evolve
wrote any practical or observed
limitations on modeling
Illusions
ah um
yeah it's really
hard
um one of the challenges
is most models that we use that I use
that like deep Learning Community uses
they're not fobi you don't have a a
center of gaze and you also don't have
um like a time I mean most convolutional
neural networks I'm using these kind of
recurrent neural networks but time is
not as big clearly defined in these
models as it is in a continuous time
setting for for human undergoing an
illusion trial um and I think the
combination of these two of the fact
that as a human for most things uh your
gaze you're shifting locations and your
gaze and a lot of these Illusions are
dependent on like you looking to a
particular area a lot of cognitive
science tests and so I think it would be
really helpful if we had models that
yeah I mean learn you can think of this
as a type of action right of learning
where to move your gaze one of the
simplest possible actions and uh that
would help a lot for being able to model
Illusions and just I mean for me it's
like I read a paper of some cognitive
science experiment or about some
illusion and it's I I think of okay can
I put this data set into my model and
test it and most of the time the answer
is no because I don't have a model that
looks around or has a restricted field
of view something like that um so yeah I
think that's one of the limitations
another one
is
um the models that we're training you
have to think about what you train your
model on before you test it on the
illusion because that has a huge impact
so it's like do I train this
on amness digits or do I train it on
imag net do I train it on natural video
the the ideal thing would be to train it
on a huge data set of natural video to
say it's like now it's kind of like
learning what a human sees and then you
test it on these illusion data sets but
obviously then you're going to need a
huge model and uh yeah makes it
experiment much more complicated so
that's one of the Practical
limitations wow great answer makes me
think of a paper with letters rotating
on a table that's the digit rotation
task and then great points about the
foliation and the Dynamics of the
illusion I think you actually did
mention an illusion which is however you
mentioned in the generalization context
which is rotating on the two-dimensional
screen doesn't generalize to three
dimensions and that dimensional collapse
or reduction is the basis of the cube
projection Illusions and Cube and figure
rotation Illusions it's on your screen
and there's a silhouette or there's some
ambiguous stimuli that a generative it's
near criticality or bifurcation in the
generative model so it could represent
it one way or another way and so a lot
of the switching Illusions are just
based upon the flatness of
images and the limitations in
generalization that are revealed by
that right
yeah yeah I think there's even some work
sorry there's some work where they you
can argue people have a kind of
three-dimensional image in their heads
like even Nancy kwish had a or her lab
had a paper on this recently but and
showing yeah I don't know do do our
models have that it's not
super anyway yeah that's pretty
interesting um all right from upcycle
Club in the chat they wrote Kudos is it
true that by inducing sparsity Beyond a
certain threshold runaway behavior in
artificial neural networks is triggered
depending on the task architecture and
spar I ification
method um H I'm not sure what they mean
by runaway Behavior
but
um yeah I think too much sparsity is is
a problem and so there could be a point
uh where the model is no longer able to
learn nearly as effectively if you
imagine you only want a single neuron to
be active for every example
uh your model is going to be trying to
memorize the data set to some extent or
something like this um and you're not
going to have enough capacity so yeah I
think tuning that level of sparsity is
certainly uh an important factor um and
yeah when you look at the
likelihood if you're talking if you're
doing a generative modeling framework
typically this is balanced automatically
with the likelihood itself um if you're
you're not doing gener modeling you just
have a sparcity penalty you're going to
want to tune that
parameter okay they added just just to
clarify runaway behavior in artificial
neural networks can refer to a phenomena
where the network becomes unstable or
chaotic due to various factors such as
feedback loops noise or adversarial
inputs yeah I guess I haven't looked at
this in in like a recurrent setting
where you would get feedback
loops
um but I could yeah I could see as
serial examples being
potentially affected by your level of
sparcity
um the interesting point is would would
you be more susceptible or less
susceptible to examples I don't
know well sparsification
projecting from a fully connected higher
dimensional model just into
progressively
smaller it's pretty well understood in
general what the trade-offs are it's
easier computations a smaller model
sparer the basy graph is going to be
clearer to represent and then also it
will have all of the other trade-offs
with false positive and negatives of
generalizing but that's why it's an
iterative fit process
so I guess how does
your sparsification
approach
balance does it use AIC or Bic or some
other model fitting approach to
determine the relevant sparsification
for a given
input how do you determine H how like
like in lasso regression like how how do
you know how how much how do you
threshold how many how sparse you want
it to
be right yeah I think there's a lot of
good literature on this and even so some
people like D at at Harvard and some
people I'm working with now uh have done
these
kind of
unrolled um iterative sparsification
networks where it's like a recurrent
roll Network and it iteratively sparsify
and you can show that this yields
something like Rel or uh group act like
group AC group sparse activations like
we're using here um in this setting uh
it's really just by having this um this
construction of this T
variable where we have Z on top and uh
and then it's in some effect gated by
these the sum of U variables in the
bottom so w maybe I wasn't super clear
about this is a matrix that is
connecting that's what defines the
groups when I'm defining the group
sparcity uh that connects all these Ed
together and so the idea is uh like here
if all of go to one of the other
examples if all of your
's uh are not active for a given
t or if all of your us are active for a
given t uh that t variable is going to
be very small right because your
denominator is going to be very big and
that induces sparcity so it's uh it's a
constraint satisfaction if you have a if
you have a set of U's that are all small
uh then that that constraint is
satisfied and now Z is allowed to kind
of Express itself and that's what
then uh kind of yeah achieves the sparse
Activation so this is induced by these
two uh K Divergence terms here these are
saying like how far is the hu and HZ
from a gausian and then through this
construction of the student T variable
we're effectively constructing a sparse
prior distribution just from these
gaussin but in terms of the act the
actual objective uh the terms and the
objective that we're optimizing are just
these two KL terms that are pushing it
towards sparity to some extent and this
is balanced automatically with the
likelihood term here through the decoder
so we don't have terms that we're tuning
but we're learning the parameters of
these different encoders and then
analyzing the pale
divergences cool all right another
question from Dave Douglas who
wrote speaking of gaze and illusion can
the studies on constancies in and
infants be separated into lower level
illusion relevant neural activities
versus perhaps higher level conceptual
constancy uh can you read it again sorry
I don't know yeah speaking of gaze and
illusion the two features that you
highlighted were absent
from the current kind of architecture
might the studies on constancies in ill
in
infants cognitive constancies be
separated into lower level illusion
relevant neural activities versus
perhaps higher level conceptual
constancy ah interesting
um yeah probably I'm not I'm not
uh an expert or actually even very
familiar with like object permanency
studies and infants and and constancy
stuff so but I think that would be
incredibly interesting to study in in
neural network architectures and that
was kind of some of the idea with this
uh illusion that I was trying to model
down here with this line I don't know if
I was super clear about this but the top
row is the input and we're effectively
like blocking the input for a single
frame and I wanted to see does the
network kind of encode that that that
the thing is still there when that frame
is gone can I still decode the presence
of the object from the neural activity
uh and then what is it also inferring
about the motion because of the fact
that it saw the bars at a slightly
different location than from before when
the after the frame is gone um so yeah I
think there's definitely multiple levels
to it um where some would probably be
much lower level and
uh maybe long-term object permanency I
would guess would be significantly
higher level um
it just makes me think of those
experiments with cats back in the day
where it's like they raised them in
darkness except for an hour a day they
put them in Vertical World or horizontal
world where they only saw horizontal
lines or vertical lines uh and you can
see the the organization of their cortex
changes like they have less receptivity
to horizontal lines if they've never
seen horizontal lines before and then
you take a stick and you wave it in
front of their face and if the stick is
horizontal they just they do nothing if
it's vertical they're swatting at it
they're trying to hit it it's like they
just literally don't see it at all if
there's a horizontal bar in front of
their face so I think in that case then
this is evidence of a low-level
deficiency and vision uh contributing to
some sort of an illusion so I I think
yeah there could certainly be some
aspect to that in infant as
well one very curious point you brought
up was the animate and
inanimate manifold with small things
being
intermediate right what does that
represent or or is it because they're
handleable or it might be an insect or
it might be something that might move
away just with wind or what does that
say right yeah uh so this is work by
like conl I think was the one who
discovered this um organization and they
they tried to figure it out and they
think I I don't I might be getting this
wrong so I recommend people to read her
work on that if they call it tripartite
organization but if I remember correctly
they did a lot of follow-up work on why
it's there's this organization and some
evidence points to kind of mid-level
statistics
of curvature of these objects and kind
of like the distance that you see
objects from or
like um animate objects or maybe more
curvy or there's there regardless of
what the actual answer is there were a
lot of different hypotheses that were
stemming from like properties of these
objects um maybe midlevel or lowlevel
properties more so than higher level
properties I still don't know if it's
exactly been solved of whether it's like
interaction like you said with the
object causes the separation or
um or yeah the general shapes of these
objects I would bet as with most things
it's like some combination of all of the
above uh but I think the interesting
thing from this modeling point of view
is that
um this is only trained on correlation
statistics from the image data sets
itself this has no interaction this has
no notion of animacy uh
I mean this is really just training a
model on imag net just images of dogs
cats boats whatever and yet it still
achieves this type of organization so
there's some sort of it could be
semantic characteristics right we have
IM we have a network that can classify
boats versus dogs versus 20 other breeds
of dogs uh but it it might also have
some correspondant with lower level
statistics as
well so yeah I don't know I guess he my
answer
yeah and also very provocative analogy
was the translational
shift in the mnist in the handwriting
recognition
setting what are the translational
shifts
that exist today what's the three pixel
example is that some prompt engineered
attack on an L or something or something
a special character being inserted or or
a um uh some overlay on an image that we
can't even detect that so what do you
think those challenges are and what are
ways that we can pursue
that yeah absolutely I mean I think kind
of the way I was thinking about it is
like these symmetry
Transformations um if you're thinking
about language models you can imagine a
symmetry transformation it's just like
replacing a word with a synonym or
something uh you have the sentence to us
means the exact same thing but now
suddenly the model is going to respond
very differently
um or or or like translation between
languages right uh this can be seen as a
type of transformation it preserves the
underlying meaning of the input to us
but so the model it looks completely
different and we would like to have
models which behave in a predictable way
with respect to the types of
Transformations because I think humans
behave very predictably with the type of
these Transformations and when we're
dealing with AI systems we expect them
to also behave that way and I think
that's part of what causes a lot of
challenges interacting with these
systems and I kind of tried to do a a
rough cheeky demonstration of that with
with this bear and and squares and stuff
like um we
expect it to be able to do something
simple like this because we think most
humans could and yet it doesn't and if
you imagine this is a critical scenario
where you expect this and that's a big
problem um how do we handle that that's
I think that's kind of the what I'm
searching for I
think
my direction I'm taking it is looking
for
more simple and like bottom up building
blocks of neural network architectures
or algorithms that kind of yield these
emergent structural properties and I
think that's a much more generalizable
way rather than building something on
top of what we already have um I think
that's something that will scale much
better and also matches more with the
brain
does very cool one kind of
implementational question what are the
computational requirements of just
running this or what's the data like of
being a student or researcher running
variants of these like do they use
terabytes of data and you're using large
computation or is this something that
people can run on their own
laptops I think almost everything I
presented today can be run locally so
like this stuff is super simple you can
run I mean you're G you're I think you
can run it on your laptop if you want to
like train and experiment with different
things it's going to be pretty slow so
I'd recommend
some commercial GPU like a I I run
pretty much everything on like Nvidia
1080s pretty old pretty cheap but they
have 12 gigs of RAM or whatever and it's
kind of more than enough for these
models most of these are only a couple
gigabytes of RAM I think one thing that
some people think is weird is I do most
of my experiments on stuff like mest so
it's 32 by 32 pixel images because I can
train it small and locally
um if you want to do stuff
like uh like yeah most my experiments
are on
Mists if you want to do stuff like this
it's are much more complicated this
hamiltonian Dynamic Suite here you're
getting into bigger models that are
running across multiple gpus and so here
I was using a cluster to run these types
of models um but I'd say most of these
types of ideas you can start to play
with on a a single machine with the GPU
is is more than enough U or even just
like in a collab notebook um something
like that if you want to train something
on image net it gets more complicated uh
and you
need at least one GPU ideally more but
yeah I don't do a whole lot of big scale
stuff yet I think it's certainly
interesting and there's definitely a lot
more you can do there but for some of
these kind of simpler or more
fundamental questions I don't know what
you want to call it um a smaller machine
is nice and fast
so cool
useful all right I'll read a comment
from
Dave recalling Bert dev's comment during
the applied active inference Symposium
about the desirability of spending less
effort or ATP on foraging or control
situations where we don't need much
Precision I don't know if you listen to
this but Professor devise mentioned
about variable Precision models and how
they could be used to enable different
features of generalization and actual
structural course training as well as
like reduced computational
requirements does he have any
suggestions on how to introduce this
distinction into active inference Theory
what kinds of experiments could Winkle
this
out oh wow yeah that's something I don't
I don't think I have too much
intelligent to say about to be
completely honest
um h
it's super interesting question because
I think the intuition makes a lot of
sense to me that uh you're talking
about if I understand correctly variable
rates of precision when you're encoding
and or or in your model in general doing
computation
um that somehow has an impact on your
your future performance as a relation to
some energy store I think yeah and if
you wanted to build this into an active
inference system you would need to
have really an embodied system where the
agent has some notion of energy like an
internal energy store
and yeah some something that is trying
to conserve while it's performing its
actions uh and running out of energy
would need to mean something bad for the
agent um and then maybe you could
observe kind of an emergence
uh reduction
and en coding Precision or something
like this as as the agent is trying to
learn to act more effectively you might
have to give it an ability to control
its Precision um yeah like I
said definitely out of my expertise but
it's thoughts cool okay on this slide
right here first very cool image it's
kind of like
a digital a and
poic
um if it were a simpler
input or reduced
data size or just reduced complexity of
patterns or if it were an increased
complexity how would this image look
different yeah so I did some experiments
trying to change
these orientation columns
and um you can yeah basically changing
the parameters of the model you can get
these columns to be bigger you can get
them to not have very similar structure
to what we see in the humans where we
have you you can get them to have more
bands of activity um and it also like
you said it depends on the data set that
you're using if I use like really simple
sinusoidal gradings as input I get
something like this if I use rotating
nness digits I get something that's a
little bit more uh rotational curvy
higher entropy um
so I think these are all interesting
things if you want to study the
emergence of the type of organization in
an natural system uh if you have a model
that now yields different Organization
for different settings that's a great
way to see okay then what settings best
match our observed data um so so yeah I
can I can send those around if you're
interested but um
yeah I think one also other sorry one
one other interesting point there is
that the uh different animals have
different types of uh orientation
selectivity and different numbers of pin
Wheels some animals don't have it at all
I think maybe mice if I'm correct have
this kind of uh they call Salt and
Pepper selectivity so it's basically
random you don't have any sort of like
topographic orientation stivity um so
there is evidence that yeah different
systems do this differently and and it's
interesting to figure out
why yeah this very cool it reminds me of
first the reaction
diffusion visual space where there's
different SK skin patterns and fur and
bands and Speckles and then
also um these islands of activity enable
the multiplexing which you described
with encapsulation through through space
and time so it's actually um possible
that a region might have no activity
from a
given granularity like if it was being
looked at at fmri spatial and temporal
time
scale if the pockets of activity first
off if they're even reflected by what is
being measured but but if the pockets of
activity are slow or
faster then that measurement is going to
not be different than noise it'll all
have been averaged out so then there
might be some yeah interesting th like
data sets that do actually have a lot of
richness but then for one reason or
another it just was averaged out over
because it wasn't being connected to the
right
scale
absolutely I think that is one of the
main main reason that uh reasons that
that traveling waves in the brain have
been difficult to study to this point
and there's a fantastic review by thi
and vile Miller nature reviews where um
they
basically go through all the evidence of
traveling waves and there and they go
and show like uh if you're averaging
over
trials uh you're going to complet miss
this traveling wave activity it's going
to look like some mean value or
something like this you really need to
go at the single trial level and need to
have high enough spatial Revolution such
that it's you know it satisfies nous
frequencies uh and and this just is
something that people didn't do for a
long time especially if you're doing
single electric recordings you're not
going to see a traveling wave you're
going to see oscillations um so you need
like multi- electrode arrays and
basically they're saying okay yeah now
that we have the technology to do this
is one
we're seeing this structure that that
exists that we didn't see before and
potentially this is an explanation for a
lot of the noise that we were seeing
before maybe it really is just traveling
waves um so yeah I think there's a lot
to be done in the future with
increased abilities for
recording that's very
cool well any final thoughts or
questions or where are you going to take
this
work yeah no thanks for having me
um hopefully in the active infrast
Direction that's that's I would love to
I think it'll be super fun so yeah I'm
not really sure I'm looking at Maybe
music uh right now um looking at
uh other kind of crazy directions I
don't want to sound too crazy uh but I
I'll go down
yeah a lot of things so one one thing
that's coming up something we submitted
to nurs is studying memory with
traveling waves um so that paper just
came out on archive today of how waves
are really good at encoding long-term
memories which I think is super
interesting so I might go a little more
in that
direction sounds good and yes would be
very exciting to see action come into
play when there was the neurons that
stay Act even as the dogs feet were
moving there's a lot of like action
sequences like throwing a baseball and
then it goes and it's like there's
something about that action that's
continuing to influence and so having
like a deep temporal representation of
alternative
actions and then the variational
autoencoder is already
basically the right Basi and statistical
architecture
[Music]
to discuss the variational and the
expected free energy so I think it's a
very promising
area yeah I'm I'm super excited about
that so I really hope to to get over
there and happy that if people have
ideas I would love to hear from you via
email or anything like that
so really appreciate it all right thank
you till next
time thanks so much
bye by e